Adam N. Goodkind

CONTACT Information Northwestern University
Department of Communication Studies
2240 Campus Drive, Evanston, IL 60208 USA

 ${\it a.goodkind@u.northwestern.edu} \\ {\it adamgoodkind.com}$

RESEARCH STATEMENT I study social interactions through the lens of keystroke timing, using HCI theories in combination with linguistic analysis. My thesis is titled *Using keystrokes to predict social dynamics in online dialogue*. It identifies how we can use timing differences in keystrokes to recover many of the same social cues we usually detect in signals such as tone-of-voice or pauses, but are lost in text-based digital communication. The thesis brings together HCI, Cognitive Science, NLP and statistical modeling. I have a passion for applying findings from HCI to creating more useful tools for users, alongside creating engaging visualizations to improve understanding.

EDUCATION

PhD, Northwestern University

Media, Technology & Society Program

2019-Present

PI: Darren Gergle (CollabLab)

Dissertation: Using keystrokes to predict social dynamics in online dialogue

Linguistics Department

2016-2019

PI: Klinton Bicknell (Language & Computation Lab)

Honors:

Data Science Fellowship Cognitive Science Specialist

M.A., CUNY Graduate Center

2016

Computational Linguistics

M.A. Thesis: Utilizing Linguistic Context To Improve Identification in Typed Text Thesis Advisors: Prof. Andrew Rosenberg and Prof. Martin Chodorow

B.A., Columbia University

2007

Religion (Study of Science & Religion)

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant, CollabLab, Evanston, IL, USA

2019-Present

PI: Darren Gergle

- Running a crowdsourced experiment for my dissertation utilizing keystroke-level analysis to understand and predict both social and cognitive differences in keystroke timing and linguistic choices.
- Creating machine learning models, including neural networks, to predict social dynamics based on keystroke timing.
- Supervise a Research Assistant tasked with creating a JavaScript interface and setting up a database for experiments.

$\textbf{Research Assistant,} \ \text{LangComp Lab, Evanston, IL, USA}$

2017-2019

PI: Klinton Bicknell

- Researched how linguistic predictability, measured with neural language models, affects sentence processing via eye-tracking.
- Investigated autism diagnoses using linguistic markers, using semantic similarity (word vectors) and pragmatic deficiencies.

 ${\bf Research~Assistant,~CUNY~Speech~Lab,~New~York,~NY,~USA}$

2012-2016

PI: Andrew Rosenberg

Managed DARPA-funded initiative to improve security and personal authentication in computer use, by predicting keystroke and language patterns with machine learning algorithms.

Research Assistant, Columbia NLP Group, New York, NY, USA

2006-2007

PI: Rebecca Passonneau

Non-Academic Employment

PhD Data Science Intern, Vail Systems, Chicago, IL, USA

Summer 2020

Created experiments to empirically evaluate the quality of text-to-speech (TTS) systems

Software Developer in Test Intern, Microsoft, Redmond, WA, USA Summer 2013

- Developed website (back- and front-end) to diagnose licensing issues with Microsoft products
- Developed decision-making pipeline to aid in issue diagnosis

Operations Analyst, Goldman Sachs, Multiple Locations, USA

2008-2011

- Team Leader for Technology Enhancements
- Created software to streamline daily asset delivery workflow, from 3 hours to 25 minutes

LANGUAGES

Computer: Java, Python, R (ggplot2, plotly, lme4), C++, LATEX, Decent with {HTML, JavaScript, React, CSS}

Human: American Sign Language (ASL), Hebrew, Latin

Honors and Awards

Dissertation Research Support, Northwestern Dept. of Communication Studies 2022 Incubation Prize, Hack4Rare Hackathon (Recursion Pharmaceuticals & CTF) 2021 Best Paper Award, Cognitive Modeling & Computational Linguistics (CMCL) 2018 Developmental Sciences Cluster Fellowship - Finalist, Northwestern University 2018 Data Science Fellowship, Northwestern University 2016-2017 USS Donald and Mary Ellen Passantino Scholarship, CUNY Graduate Center 2015Google Lime Connect Scholarship-Finalist 2014 Thomas W. Smith Academic Fellowship, CUNY Graduate Center 2013-2014 National Science Foundation, Undergraduate Research Grant, Columbia University 2007 Albert A. List Academic Fellowship 2003-2007 King's Crown Award for Outstanding Leadership, Columbia University 2006

SELECT PUBLICATIONS

2021 **Goodkind, A.** TypeShift: A User Interface for Visualizing the Typing Production Process. [arXiv paper]

Goodkind, A., Bicknell, K. Local word statistics affect reading times independently of surprisal. [arXiv paper]

- 2020 **Goodkind**, **A.** An analytic model for human subjective judgements of computer-generated synthetic voice (TTS) quality. Technical Report for Vail Systems. Chicago, IL.
- 2018 Goodkind, A., Lee, M., Martin, G. E., Losh, M., & Bicknell, K. Detecting language impairments in autism: A computational analysis of semi-structured conversations with vector semantics. In *Proceedings of the Inaugural Meeting of the Society for Computation in Linguistics*. Salt Lake City, UT: Linguistic Society of America. [paper] [slides]
 - Goodkind, A. & Bicknell, K. Predictive power of word surprisal for reading times is a linear function of language model quality. In *Proceedings of the 8th Workshop on Cognitive Modeling and Computational Linguistics (CMCL 2018)*. Salt Lake City, UT: Linguistic Society of America. [paper] [slides]
- 2016 Goodkind, A., Brizan D.G. & Rosenberg, A. Utilizing Overt and Latent Linguistic Structure to Improve Keystroke-Based Authentication. Image and Vision Computing: Best of Biometrics Special Issue.
- 2015 Goodkind, A., Brizan D.G. & Rosenberg, A. *Improvements to Keystroke-Based Authentication By Adding Linguistic Context.* 7th IEEE Conference on Biometrics: Theory, Applications and Systems (BTAS 2015). (Slides)
 - Goodkind, A. & Rosenberg, A. Muddying The Multiword Expression Waters: How Cognitive Demand Affects Multiword Expression Production. 11th Workshop on Multiword Expressions at NAACL-HLT 2015. (Slides)
 - Brizan, D. G.*, **Goodkind, A.***, Koch, P., Balagani, K., Phoha, V. V., & Rosenberg, A. Utilizing Linguistically-Enhanced Keystroke Dynamics to Predict Typist Cognition and Demographics. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, October 2015, vol. 84, 57-68.

- 2014 Locklear, H., Govindarajan, S., Sitova, Z., Goodkind, A., Brizan, D., Rosenberg, A., Phoha, V., Gasti, P., & Balagani, K. Continuous Authentication with Cognition-centric Text Production and Revision Features. Biometrics (IJCB), 2014 IEEE International Joint Conference.
- 2013 Serwadda, A., Balagani, K., Wang, Z., Koch, P., Govindarajan, S., Pokala, R., Goodkind, A., Brizan, D.G., Rosenberg, A., & Phoha, V. Scan-based Evaluation of Continuous Keystroke Authentication Systems. IT Professional, 15(4), 20-23.
- 2008 Goodkind, A. Tracking the Emergence of Narrative Competence in Story Retelling. Quebec Student Journal of Linguistics, Vol. 3.
- 2007 Passonneau, R. J., Goodkind, A., & Levy, E. T. Annotation of Children's Oral Narrations: Modeling Emergent Narrative Skills for Computational Applications. Florida Artificial Intelligence Research Society (FLAIRS), 253-258.
- 2006 Passonneau, R., McKeown, K., Sigelman, S., & Goodkind, A.. Applying the Pyramid Method in the 2006 Document Understanding Conference. Proceedings of the 2006 Workshop of the Document Understanding Conference (DUC).

Presentations

- 2018 Lee, M.A., Martin, G.E., Goodkind, A., Bicknell, K., Maltman, N., Bush, L., Losh, M. A Multi-Method Approach to Characterizing Pragmatic Language Development in Individuals with FXS. Paper presented at the International Fragile X Conference, Cincinnati, OH, July, 2018
 - Goodkind, A.. Complex Data Visualization: Visualizing language production dynamics via keystroke analysis. Presentation at Inaugural Data Science Research Day, Northwestern University Institute on Complex Systems, 25 June 2018. (Slides)
 - Goodkind, A.. Demo of TypeShift software system for tracking keystroke dynamics at Individual Differences Workshop, Northwestern University, 30 May 2018. (Code)
 - Lee, M.A., Martin, G.E., **Goodkind, A.**, Bicknell, K., Maltman, N., Bush, L., Losh, M. *A longitudinal, multi-method analysis of pragmatic language in ASD and related developmental disabilities.* Poster presented at the International Society for Autism Research, May, 2018, Rotterdam, Netherlands
 - Goodkind, A. & Bicknell, K.. Low-level language statistics affect reading times independently of surprisal. Poster presentation at the 31st annual CUNY Conference on Human Sentence Processing, UC Davis, Davis, California, 15–17 March 2018.
- 2015 Goldman, N. & **Goodkind**, A.. Worth 1,⊕⊙⊕ Words: The Linguistics of Emoji and Emoji of Linguistics. SQUID X: 10th Annual Conference Showcasing Quirky and Original Ideas in Development. New York, NY April 24, 2015. (Slides)
- 2014 Goodkind, A.. Detecting Multi-word Expressions Through Typing Patterns. 15th Texas Linguistics Society Conference, Austin ,TX, October 24-26, 2014 (Slides)
 - Goodkind, A.. Detecting Multi-word Expressions in Computer Keyboard Produced Text. CUNY Research Day, New York, NY

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

Northwestern University

- Communication Studies 246: Intro to Health Communication (Prof. Kimberly Pusateri), 2021
- Communication Studies 351: Technology & Human Interaction (Prof. Darren Gergle), 2021
- Linguistics 220: Language & Society (Prof. Annette D'Onofrio), 2018
 - Guest lecture on quantitative data analysis
- Cognitive Science 210: Language & the Brain (Profs. Matt Goldrick & Mark Beeman), 2019
- Linguistics 221: Language & Prejudice (Prof. Erin Leddon), 2019